Julius Hobson Papers 001
People's Archive, MLK Library
- Series 20: Printed Materials, 1922-1976
  - Subseries 5: Books, 1922-1976
    Contains published fiction and non-fiction books and a few texts of poetry. Recurring topics include Marxist politics, the African diaspora, race relations, the civil rights movement, and African-American history and literature. It also contains a number of children's books, which appear to have been used as exhibits in a school desegregation case. A sample of authors include Eldridge Cleaver, W.E.B. DuBois, Alex Haley, Dick Gregory, C. Vann Woodward, Karl Marx, Robert Service, Kwame Nkrumah, Charles Osgood, Elijah Muhammed, Langston Hughes, John Hines, H. Rap Brown, Lewis Carroll, Che Guevera, and Joseph and Stewart Alsop. Some books are autographed either by the author, giver, or Hobson. Author or title arranges the books (when no author is given).
    - Joseph and Stewart Alsop - We Accuse!: The Story of the Mis­carriage of American Justice in the Case of J. Robert Oppen­heimer, 1954 (Box 104, Folder 19)
    - Herbert Aptheker - American Negro Slave Revolts, 1964 (Box 104, Folder 20)
    - Herbert Aptheker - A Documentary History of the Negro People in the United States, 1965 (Box 104, Folder 21)
    - Jocelyn Arundel - Simba of the White Mane, 1958 (Box 104, Folder 22)
    - Wallace W. Atwood and Helen Goss Thomas - Nations Beyond the Seas, 1930 (Box 104, Folder 23)
    - James Baldwin - The Fire Next Time, 1963 (Box 104, Folder 24)
    - Floyd B. Barbour - ed. - The Black Power Revolt, 1968 (Box 104, Folder 25)
    - Berg, 1970 (Box 104, Folder 26)
    - Albert P. Blaustein and Robert L. Zangrando - Civil Rights and the American Negro, 1969 (Box 104, Folder 27)
    - Guy L. Bond - Down Our Way, 1962 (Box 104, Folder 28)
    - Guy L. Bond - Once Upon A Storytime, 1962 (Box 104, Folder 29)
    - Guy L. Bond - Stories from Everywhere, 1962 (Box 104, Folder 30)
    - Simeon Booker - Black Man's America, 1964 (Box 104, Folder 31)
    - Malcom Boyd - Free to Live, 1967 (Box 104, Folder 32)
    - James Bowman et al. - ed - Of Education and Human Community, 1971 (Box 104, Folder 33)
    - Henry W. Boynton - ed. - Selected Poems, 1922 (Box 104, Folder 34)
    - Frederick K. Branom - Geography of Our World, 1929 (Box 104, Folder 35)
    - William F. Brazziel - Quality Education for All Americans, 1974 (Box 104, Folder 36)
    - Robert H. Bremner - From the Depths: The Discovery of Poverty in the United States, 1964 (Box 104, Folder 37)
    - H. Rap Brown - Die Nigger Die!, 1969 (Box 104, Folder 38)
    - Joseph C. Brown et al. - Champion Arithmetics, 1933 (Box 104, Folder 39)
    - Caedmon Records - Alexander Pope, Undated (Box 104, Folder 40)
    - Stokely Carmichael and Charles V. Hamilton - Black Power, 1967 (Box 104, Folder 41)
    - Jack Carpenter - Destination Tomorrow, 1972 (Box 104, Folder 42)
    - Lewis Carroll - Alice in Wonderland, 1946 (Box 104, Folder 43)
    - Edna W. Chandler - Cowboy Sam, 1958 (Box 104, Folder 44)
    - Che Guevera - Socialism and Man, 1966 (Box 104, Folder 45)
    - Kenneth B. Clark - Negro Protest: James Baldwin, 1963 (Box 104, Folder 46)
    - Kenneth B. Clark - A Possible Reality, 1972 (Box 104, Folder 47)
    - Eldridge Cleaver - Soul on Ice, 1968 (Box 104, Folder 48)
    - Contact Washington: An Educator's Directory, 1966 (Box 104, Folder 49)
    - Arthur W. Cook - Africa: Past and Present, 1965 (Box 104, Folder 50)
    - Basil Davidson - Which Way Africa?: The Search for a New Society, 1967 (Box 104, Folder 51)
    - Basil Davidson - The African Slave Trade, 1961 (Box 104, Folder 52)
    - Angela Y. Davis - If They Come in the Morning: Voices of Resistance, 1971 (Box 104, Folder 53)
    - Dialogue from the Ghetto, Undated (Box 104, Folder 54)
    - Henry M. Dressler - A Call for World Revolution: To Establish Perfected Society for All Mankind in the Brotherhood of Man, 1996 (Box 104, Folder 55)
    - Ivar Berg - Education and Jobs: The Great Training Robbery, 1970 (Box 104, Folder 56)
    - W.E.B. DuBois - The Souls of Black Folk, 1961 (Box 104, Folder 57)
    - Fletcher Durell - The New Day Arithmetics, 1931 (Box 104, Folder 58)
    - Clements Dutt - Fundamentals of Marxism‑Leninism, 1961 (Box 104, Folder 59)
    - Charles P. Emerson - Livinq at Our Best: Book Two, 1936 (Box 104, Folder 60)
    - The Face of Red China: The First Television Report by CBS, December 1958 (Box 104, Folder 61)
    - Frantz Fanon - Toward the African Revolution, 1967 (Box 104, Folder 62)
    - Dorothy Canfield Fisher - A Fair World for All, 1966 (Box 104, Folder 63)
    - Michael J. Flax - Blacks and Whites, 1971 (Box 104, Folder 64)
    - John E. Fleming - The Lengthening Shadow of Slavery, 1976 (Box 104, Folder 65)
    - Osmond K. Fraenkel - The Supreme Court and Civil Liberties, 1963 (Box 104, Folder 66)
    - John Hope Franklin - From Slavery to Freedom, 1947 (Box 104, Folder 67)
    - The Fraser Institute - Rent Control: A Popular Paradox, 1975 (Box 104, Folder 68)
    - Eli Ginzberg - The Negro Challenge to the Business Community, 1964 (Box 104, Folder 69)
    - Hugh Davis Graham - Violence in America: Historical and Com­parative Perspective, 1969 (Box 104, Folder 70)
    - Alexander Gray -The Development of Economic Doctrine, 1946 (Box 104, Folder 71)
    - Dick Gregory - From the Back of the Bus, 1962 (Box 104, Folder 72)
    - Dick Gregory - Nigger, 1964 (Box 104, Folder 73)
    - William H. Grier and Price M. Cobbs - The Jesus Bag, 1971 (Box 104, Folder 74)
    - Janet Harris and Julius Hobson - Black Pride: A People's Struggle, 1969 (Box 104, Folder 75)
    - Alex Haley - The Autobiography of Malcolm X (Autographed by Hobson), 1964 (Box 104, Folder 76)
    - Alex Haley - Roots, 1976 (Box 104, Folder 77)
    - John Hines - Our Friends in Africa (2 copies), 1964 (Box 104, Folder 78)
    - John Hines - The Adventures of Annancy, 1968 (Box 104, Folder 79)
    - John Hines - The Genius of Benjamin Banneker, 1968 (Box 104, Folder 80)
    - John Holt - How Children Fail, 1964 (Box 104, Folder 81)
    - W. Lee Hansen - Benefits, 1969 (Box 104, Folder 82)
    - Janet Harris - The Long Freedom Road: The Civil Rights Story, 1967 (Box 104, Folder 83)
    - Alger Hiss - In the Court of Public Opinion, 1957 (Box 104, Folder 84)
    - Charles F. Horne - Europe: The Mother of America, 1930 (Box 104, Folder 85)
    - Leo Huberman and Sybil May - The ABC of Socialism, 1953 (Box 104, Folder 86)
    - Leo Huberman - Man's Worldly Goods, 1936 (Box 104, Folder 87)
    - Langston Hughes and Arna Bontemp eds. - The Book of Negro Folklore, 1958 (Box 104, Folder 88)
    - Ellsworth Huntington et al.- Living Geography, 1935 (Box 104, Folder 89)
    - George L. Jackson - Blood in my Eye, 1972 (Box 104, Folder 90)
    - Christopher Jencks - Inequality, 1972 (Box 104, Folder 91)
    - Jesse J. Johnson - The Black Soldier Documented (1619‑1815), 1969 (Box 104, Folder 92)
    - Jesse J. Johnson - A Pictorial History of Black Soldiers (1619‑1969) in Peace and War, 1970 (Box 104, Folder 93)
    - Maldwyn A. Jones - American Immigration, 1960 (Box 104, Folder 94)
    - Abram Kardiner - The Mark of Oppression: Explorations in the American Negro, 1963 (Box 104, Folder 95)
    - Joseph F. Kauffman - Education, 1966 (Box 104, Folder 96)
    - James F. Kirham et al. - Assassination and Political Violence, 1969 (Box 104, Folder 97)
    - Ellis 0. Knox - Democracy and the District of Columbia Public Schools: A Study of Recently Integrated Public Schools (Hobson listed as secretary‑treasurer on dust jacket of Steer­ing Com. of Citizens Against Defamation.), 1957 (Box 104, Folder 98)
    - Jonathan Kozol - Death at an Early Age: The Destruction of the Hearts and Minds of Negro Children in the Boston Public Schools, 1967 (Box 104, Folder 99)
    - Jonathan Kozol - Free Schools, 1972 (Box 104, Folder 100)
    - Ferdinand Kuhn - Commodore Perry and the opening of Japan, 1955 (Box 104, Folder 101)
    - Harold Lamb - Genghis Khan and the Mongol Horde (illus. by Elton Fax), 1954 (Box 104, Folder 102)
    - Charles R. Larson ed. - Prejudice, 1971 (Box 104, Folder 103)
    - Kenneth Lasson - Proudly We Hail: Profile of Public Citizens in Action (Includes Hobson, 1975 (Box 104, Folder 104)
    - Betsy Levin et al., 1973 (Box 104, Folder 105)
    - C.Day Lewis - The Collected Poems of Wilfred Owen, 1963 (Box 104, Folder 106)
    - Hylan Lewis - Blackways of Kent, 1955 (Box 104, Folder 107)
    - Max Lerner ed - The Portable Veblen, 1970 (Box 104, Folder 108)
    - Richard A. Lester - Economics of Labor, 1946 (Box 104, Folder 109)
    - Lincoln Filene Center for Citizenship and Public Affairs - Negro Self‑Concept: Implication for School and Citizenship, 1965 (Box 104, Folder 110)
    - C. Eric Lincoln - The Black Muslims in America, 1961 (Box 104, Folder 111)
    - Louis E. Lomax - The Reluctant African, 1960 (Box 104, Folder 112)
    - Louis E. Lomax - When the Word is Given, 1963 (Box 104, Folder 113)
    - Alan Lomax ed. - 300 Years of Black Poetry, 1970 (Box 104, Folder 114)
    - Albert Luthuli - Let My People Go, 1962 (Box 104, Folder 115)
    - W. R. McConnell - Living in the Americas, 1930 (Box 104, Folder 116)
    - May McNeer - War Chief of the Seminoles, 1954 (Box 104, Folder 117)
    - Clarence Major - The New Black Poetry, 1969 (Box 104, Folder 118)
    - F. Ray Marshall - The Negro and Apprenticeship, 1967 (Box 104, Folder 119)
    - Karl Marx - Capital - Vol. 3, 1975 (Box 104, Folder 120)
    - Karl Marx - The Communist Manifesto, 1970 (Box 104, Folder 121)
    - Karl Marx - The Grundrisse, 1971 (Box 104, Folder 122)
    - David Mermelstein ed. - Economics, 1970 (Box 104, Folder 123)
    - George R. Metcalf - Black Profiles, 1968 (Box 104, Folder 124)
    - Merle Miller - Plain Speaking: An Oral Biography of Harry Truman, 1973 (Box 104, Folder 125)
    - C. Wright Mills - White Collar, 1956 (Box 104, Folder 126)
    - C. Wright Mills - The Power Elite, 1959 (Box 104, Folder 127)
    - Frederick Morteller and Daniel P. Moynihan - On Equality of Educational Opportunity, 1972 (Box 104, Folder 128)
    - Pauli Murray - Dark Testament and Other Poems, 1970 (Box 104, Folder 129)
    - Elijah Muhammad - Message to the Blackman in America, 1965 (Box 104, Folder 130)
    - N. P. Neilson - Physical Education for Elementary Schools, 1932 (Box 104, Folder 131)
    - William L. Nida - Explorers and Pioneers, 1935 (Box 104, Folder 132)
    - Kwame Nkruma - I Speak Of Freedom: A Statement of Africa, 1961 (Box 104, Folder 133)
    - Roland Oliver - A Short History of Africa, 1969 (Box 104, Folder 134)
    - The Oxford Book of American Verse, 1950 and 1939 (Box 104, Folder 135)
    - Charles E. Osgood - An Alternative to War or Surrender, 1964 (Box 104, Folder 136)
    - James Peck - Freedom Ride, 1962 (Box 104, Folder 137)
    - Tillie S. Pine and Joseph Levine - The Egyptians Knew, 1964 (Box 104, Folder 138)
    - Harry and David Posen - But Not Next Door, 1962 (Box 104, Folder 139)
    - Dudley Randall - The Black Poets, 1972 (Box 104, Folder 140)
    - Randall Dudley - For Malcom X: Poems of the Life and Death of Malcolm X, 1965 (Box 104, Folder 141)
    - Saunders Redding - The Negro, 1967 (Box 104, Folder 142)
    - Quentin Reynolds - The Battle of Britain, 1953 (Box 104, Folder 143)
    - Mendel Rivers - Essential Works of Marxism, 1965 (Box 104, Folder 144)
    - Samuel J. Roker - Vox Nigri, 1963 (Box 104, Folder 145)
    - Reed Sarralt - The Ordeal of Desegregation: The First Decade, 1966 (Box 104, Folder 146)
    - Ann Herbert Scott - Sam, 1967 (Box 104, Folder 147)
    - Robert Service - Ballads of a Bohemian, 1944 (Box 104, Folder 148)
    - Robert Service - Collected Poems, 1961 (Box 104, Folder 149)
    - Peter S. Seymour - Together We Walk, 1971 (Box 104, Folder 150)
    - Charles E. Silberman - Crisis in Black and White, 1964 (Box 104, Folder 151)
    - Jerome Skolnick and Elliott Currie - Crisis in American Institutions - 2nd edit, 1973 (Box 104, Folder 152)
    - Agnes Smedley - The Great Road: The Life and Times of Chuteh, 1956 (Box 104, Folder 153)
    - Social Change and the Mental Health of Children, 1973 (Box 104, Folder 154)
    - Alexander Solzhenitsyn, August 14 1972 (Box 104, Folder 155)
    - Stephen Spender - Selected Poems, 1964 (Box 104, Folder 156)
    - Chuck Stone - Black Political Power in America, 1968 (Box 104, Folder 157)
    - Paul M‑Sweezy - The Theory of Capitalist Development, 1942 (Box 104, Folder 158)
    - A Time to Listen A Time to Act: Voices from the Ghettos of the Nation's Cities (Hobson cited within), 1967 (Box 104, Folder 159)
    - M. B. Tolson - Harlem Gallery - Book I - The Curator, 1965 (Box 104, Folder 160)
    - A Treasury of the World's Best Loved Poems, 1961 (Box 104, Folder 161)
    - Urban American Inc. - One Year Later: An Assessment of the Nation's Response to the Crisis Describe the National Commission on Civil Disorders, 1969 (Box 104, Folder 162)
    - Edward Wakin - Black Fighting Men in U.S. History, 1971 (Box 104, Folder 163)
    - Washington: An Educator's Directory, 1966 (Box 104, Folder 164)
    - Arthur I. Waskow - The Freedom Seder, 1969 (Box 104, Folder 165)
    - Gerald Weinstein - Toward Humanistic Education: A Curriculum of Affect, 1970 (Box 104, Folder 166)
    - Irvin Wiley and Hirst D. Milhollen - Embattled Confederates, 1964 (Box 104, Folder 167)
    - C. Vann Woodward - The Strange Career of Jim Crow, 1966 (Box 104, Folder 168)
    - Kathleeen Wright - The Other American, 1969 (Box 104, Folder 169)
    - Whitney M. Young, 1969 (Box 104, Folder 170)
    - K. Zilliacus - A New Birth of Freedom, 1958 (Box 104, Folder 171)
- Series 21: Photographs and oversized items, ca. 1965-1977
  This series contains photographs of Hobson in groups at political and social events or single portraits of him. Most of the photographs are oversized mounted enlargements but also included are standard-sized prints, snapshots, and negatives. A few oversized items such as certificates, awards, and medical x-rays and included in this series.
  - Oversized mounted photographs, Undated (Box 105, Folder 1)
  - Oversized mounted photographs, Undated (Box 106, Folder 1)
  - Oversized photographs, negatives, x-rays, and campaign memorabilia, Undated (Box 107, Folder 1)